Guide to the James Lord Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Lord papers
1909-2008
1946-2003
GEN MSS 790
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
35.63
(88 boxes)
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by James Lord in the course of his activities as an art critic and writer, and includes drafts of writings, research material, correspondence, photographs, and audiovisual recordings. Correspondence (Series I) is both personal and professional, and relates chiefly to the artistic and literary world of mid- and late-twentieth-century Paris. Writings (Series II) include Lord's extensive research files, drafts, and primary sources for Giacometti: A Biography. Drafts and correspondence relating to Lord's memoirs, including letters from his mother that he used as source material for Six Exceptional Women: Further Memoirs (1994), are also filed in the Writings series. Visual Material (Series III) includes photographs of Pablo Picasso by Lord and an unidentified photographer, and photographs of Lord in the 1950s and 1960s, including portraits by Henri Cartier-Bresson. Series III also includes drawings by Jean Cocteau and others. Audiovisual recordings (Series IV) relate chiefly to Lord's research on Alberto Giacometti and include interviews and lectures. Personal Papers (Series V) consist of Lord's 1960 passport and fragmentary portions of his journals. Printed Material (Series VI) consists chiefly of clippings and magazine articles related to Lord and his research. A small amount of printed ephemera is also filed in Series VI.
Lord, James, 1922-2009
Existence and Location of Copies
Reference copies of sound recordings are available.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Lord, 1982-2009, unless otherwise noted on folder labels.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 80-81 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Materials
Other material by or relating to James Lord can be found by searching Orbis (Yale's Online Catalog).
James Lord also donated artwork to the Yale University Art Gallery.
James Lord, 1922-2009
James Lord was an American writer and art critic who lived in France from 1945 until his death. He authored several works on the artist Alberto Giacometti, including A Giacometti Portrait (1965), Alberto Giacometti Drawings (1971), Giacometti: A Biography (1985), and Mythic Giacometti (2004). His memoirs and portraits of the artistic and literary world include Picasso and Dora: A Personal Memoir (1993), Six Exceptional Women: Further Memoirs (1994), Some Remarkable Men: Further Memoirs (1996), and My Queer War (2010).
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by James Lord in the course of his activities as an art critic and writer, and includes drafts of writings, research material, correspondence, photographs, and audiovisual recordings. Correspondence (Series I) is both personal and professional, and relates chiefly to the artistic and literary world of mid- and late-twentieth-century Paris. Writings (Series II) include Lord's extensive research files, drafts, and primary sources for Giacometti: A Biography. Drafts and correspondence relating to Lord's memoirs, including his letters from his mother that he used as source material for Six Exceptional Women: Further Memoirs (1994), are also filed in the Writings series. Visual Material (Series III) includes photographs of Pablo Picasso by Lord and an unidentified photographer, and photographs of Lord in the 1950s and 1960s, including portraits by Henri Cartier-Bresson. Series III also includes drawings by Jean Cocteau and others. Audiovisual recordings (Series IV) relate chiefly to Lord's research on Alberto Giacometti and include interviews and lectures. Personal Papers (Series V) consist of Lord's 1960 passport and fragmentary portions of his journals. Printed Material (Series VI) consists chiefly of clippings and magazine articles related to Lord and his research. A small amount of printed ephemera is also filed in Series VI.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Correspondence, 1946-2002. II. Writings, 1917-2003. III. Visual Material, 1924-1964. IV. Audiovisual Recordings, 1982-2002. V. Personal Papers, circa 1950-2001. VI. Printed Material, 1949-circa 2003.
Art critics; Art critics -- United States -- Archives; Art, European; Authors, American; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Autobiography; Biography; Audiovisual materials; Photographic prints; Sound recordings; Video recordings; Art critics; Authors, American; Cartier-Bresson, Henri, 1908-2004; Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963; Giacometti, Alberto, 1901-1966; Lord, James, 1922-2009; Picasso, Pablo, 1881-1973
- Correspondence, 1946-2002; Series I; 8.76; (21 boxes); 8.76 linear feet (21 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - "A" General, 1991-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Acton, Harold, 1951-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Aeschbach, Hervé, 1995-2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Albers, Josef, 1974 February 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ardoin, John, 1994-2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Arletty, 1947-1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ashbery, John
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Acton, Harold
  - "B" General, 1950, 1990-2001 (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - Bacquet, Jean Michel, 1989-2001 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Baldwin, James, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bally, Raymond E., 1998-2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Balthus, 1954-1994 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes related printed material and manuscripts.
  - Barber, Samuel, 1956-1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Barthes, Roland, 1957 November 20 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Bawer, Bruce, 1994-2001 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Beaumont, Etienne de, 1953-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 1989-2001 (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
  - Bellenger, Sylvia, 1991-1998 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Berggruen, Heinz and Bettina, 1969-1993 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Berlet, Marc, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Berthoud, Silvio, 1982-1991 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Bindster, Nils, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Binns, Graham and Jillian, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Bonnefoy, Yves
    - Incoming, 1972, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Outgoing (copy), 1992 January 1 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Bousquet, Marie-Louise, 1962 September 21 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Braque, Georges, 1959 March 1 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Burnstein, Milka, 1996-2000 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - "C" General, 1950s, 1989-2001 (Box 4, Folder 36-37)
  - Cachin, Françoise, 1994-2002 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Caetani, Marguerite, 1950-1955 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Cameron, Peter, 1997-2000 (Box 5, Folder 40-41)
  - Campbell, Tom, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Capote, Truman, 1954 February 16 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Carroll, Michael, 1998-2000 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Cartier-Bresson, Henri, 1976-1998 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Cassou, Jean, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Chagall, Marc and Vava, 1953-1960 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Chapoval, _____, 1946-1949 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Char, René, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Chatwin, Bruce, 1963 August 8 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Claudine Makes Movies, 1996-1999 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Clouzot, Marianne, 2000 November 24 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Cocteau, Jean, 1951-1963 (Box 6, Folder 53-56)
  - Cook, Mariana, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Cooper, Douglas, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    Includes a letter from Bernard Minoret to Douglas Cooper.
  - Cordell, Thomas and Morton, David, 1989-2001 (Box 6, Folder 59-61)
  - Craft, Robert, 1969 August 30 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Crane, Mrs. W. Murray, 1955-1958, undated (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Craxton, John, 1952-1996, undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Croisset, Ethel de, 1994 June 3 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - "D" General, 1989-2000 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Déon, Michel, 1969, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Dermit, Edouard, 1952 October 28 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Dubuffet, Jean, 1959, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Dufy, Raoul, 1951 November 2 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Duras, Marguerite, 1962, undated (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - "E" General, 1989-1999 (Box 7, Folder 72-73)
  - Elysium Press, 1994-2000 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - "F" General, 1990-2000 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Farrar, Straus & Giroux, 1989-2001 (Box 8, Folder 76-79)
  - Fowlie, Wallace, 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - The Frick Collection, 1990-1997 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - "G" General, 1944, 1989-2001 (Box 8, Folder 82-83)
  - Galassi, Jonathan, 1991-1999 (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Gaulle, Charles de, 1959 October 28 (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - Gelfand, Jeffrey, 1994-1998 (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - Gerwick, James, 1993-2000 (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - Giacometti, Alberto
    - Alberto Giacometti to James Lord, 1962-1965 (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - Outgoing letters to L. Lichtenlau (photocopies), 1990 (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - Incoming letter from "Caroline", 1960 June (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Giacometti, Annette
    - Incoming, 1968, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 91)
    - "Letters and papers of interest re: Alberto and Annette", 1980s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - Giacometti, Bruno and Odette, 1980-1995 (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - Gibson, Anthea and Thomas, 1991-1993 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Gilot, Françoise, 1965-2001 (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - Giroux, Vincent
    See: Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
  - Gombrich, E. H., 1979-1981 (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Goyen, William, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Guggenheim, Peggy, 1962 July 30 (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - "H" General, 1990-2003 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Harold Ober Assoc., 1990-2000 (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - Hohl, M., 1992-2000 (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - Hyde, Frederick B., 1991-1997 (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - Indiana, Robert, 1969 December 4 (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - Ivory, James, 1994-2001 (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - "J" General, 1993-2001 (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - Jeffers, Alex, 1992-2000 (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - Johnston, Jill, 1995-2000 (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - "K" General, 1952, 1989-1998 (Box 11, Folder 108)
  - Kaufmann, Eva, undated (Box 11, Folder 109)
  - Kidde, W.H., 1989-1997 (Box 11, Folder 110)
  - Kimball, Roger, incoming and outgoing (including copies), 1988-1994 (Box 11, Folder 111-112)
  - Kramer, Hilton & Esta, 1990-1992 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - "L" General, 1940-2003 (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - Lacan, Sylvia Balaille, 1982 December 29 (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - LaPautre, Michelle, 1995-2001 (Box 11, Folder 116)
  - Lieberson, Brigetta, 1998-2001 (Box 12, Folder 117)
  - Lipchitz, Jacques, 1952 December 20 (Box 12, Folder 118)
  - Lippman, Elga L., 1953 (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - Lord, Louise Bennett, incoming and outgoing, 1950-1975 (Box 12, Folder 120)
    See also: Six Exceptional Women: Further Memoirs (Series II)
  - Lord, Bennett, 1991-1999 (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - Louis-Dreyfus, Phyllis and William, 1994-2001 (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - Luce, Clare Booth, 1956 May 9 (Box 12, Folder 123)
  - "M" General, 1957-2000 (Box 12, Folder 124-125)
  - Maar, Dora, incoming and outgoing, 1954-1993, undated (Box 13, Folder 126)
  - Magny, Olivier de, 1955-2000 (Box 13, Folder 127-128)
  - Mallon, Michael, 1989-2000 (Box 13, Folder 129)
  - Mann, Thomas, 1945-1950 (Box 13, Folder 130)
  - Masson, André and Rose, 1955-1958 (Box 13, Folder 131)
  - Matisse, Henri, 1952 March 7 (Box 13, Folder 132)
  - Matisse, Patricia, 1965-1971 (Box 13, Folder 133)
  - Matisse, Pierre, 1972-1973 (Box 13, Folder 134)
  - Maugham, W. Somerset, 1945-1955 (Box 13, Folder 135)
  - Maxwell, William, 1980-2000 (Box 13, Folder 136)
  - Maxwell, William (continued), 1980-2000 (Box 14, Folder 137-139)
  - McClatchy, J.D., 1993-1995 (Box 14, Folder 140)
  - Mesnil, Gerard, 2000-2001 (Box 14, Folder 141)
  - Ministère de l'Éducation Nationale and Ministère de l'Intérieur, 1952-1963 (Box 14, Folder 142)
  - Mitchell, Joan, 1960 May 14 (Box 14, Folder 143)
  - Morton, David
    See: Cordell, Thomas
  - Musée national Picasso, 1996-2001 (Box 14, Folder 144)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1994-2001 (Box 14, Folder 145)
  - Music, Z., 1988 January 22 (Box 14, Folder 146)
  - "N" General, 1994-1999 (Box 14, Folder 147)
  - Noailles, Charles de, 1970 (Box 14, Folder 148)
  - Noailles, Marie-Laure de, 1953-1962 (Box 14, Folder 149)
  - "O" General, 1993-1996 (Box 15, Folder 150)
  - Orwell, Sonia, 1950-1961, undated (Box 15, Folder 151)
  - "P" General, 1993-2001 (Box 15, Folder 152)
  - Patmore, Derek, 1953 November 2 (Box 15, Folder 153)
  - Perdikidi, Erietta, 1959-1962 (Box 15, Folder 154)
  - Perenyi, Eleanor, 1992-1997 (Box 15, Folder 155)
  - Picasso, Claude, 1966 February 11 (Box 15, Folder 156)
  - Picasso, Pablo, 1956-1990 (Box 15, Folder 157)
    Includes clippings.
  - Pillsbury, Henry, 1999-2001 (Box 15, Folder 158)
  - Pompidou, Georges, 1972 October 6 (Box 15, Folder 159)
  - Pounder, Robert, 1994-1998 (Box 15, Folder 160)
  - "Q" General, 1996 (Box 15, Folder 161)
  - "R" General, 1951-2002 (Box 16, Folder 162-163)
  - Raskin, Larry, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 164)
  - Richardson, John, 1954, 1991-1992 (Box 16, Folder 165)
  - Roberts, Stone, 1999-2001 (Box 16, Folder 166)
  - Rodd, Nancy, 1954-1955 (Box 16, Folder 167)
  - Rorem, Ned, 1954-1999 (Box 16, Folder 168-169)
  - Rothschild, Beatrice de, 1981 March 15 (Box 16, Folder 170)
  - Rothschild, Liliane de, 1990-1993 (Box 16, Folder 171)
  - Runte, H.B., 2001 (Box 16, Folder 172)
  - Russell, Vera, 1982 February 9 (Box 16, Folder 173)
  - "S" General, 1953, 1990-2001 (Box 16, Folder 174-175)
  - Sabartés, Jaime, 1946-1947 (Box 17, Folder 176)
  - Salles, Georges, 1954, undated (Box 17, Folder 177)
  - Sassier, Inès, 1946 (Box 17, Folder 178)
  - Scott, Paul, 1953-1957 (Box 17, Folder 179)
  - Sécheret, Jean-Baptiste, 1983-1999 (Box 17, Folder 180-181)
  - Shearburn, Dudley, 1995-2000 (Box 17, Folder 182)
  - Sheehan, Vincent, 1947, undated (Box 17, Folder 183)
  - Sisson, Richard, 1998-2001 (Box 17, Folder 184)
  - Smith, William Jay, 1950, 1993-2000 (Box 17, Folder 185)
  - Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1997-2001 (Box 17, Folder 186)
  - Spender, Stephen, 1948-1985 (Box 17, Folder 187)
  - Stadler, Matthew, 1993-1999 (Box 17, Folder 188)
  - Stadler, Maury Tuckerman, 1990-1993 (Box 18, Folder 189)
  - Steegmuller, Francis, 1966-1967 (Box 18, Folder 190)
  - Stamelman, Richard and Emily, 1990-1992 (Box 18, Folder 191)
  - Stokes, Henry Scott, 1983 July 23 (Box 18, Folder 192)
  - Stravinsky, Igor, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 193)
  - Supko, John, 1998-2001 (Box 18, Folder 194-195)
  - "T" General, 1952, 1993-2001 (Box 18, Folder 196)
  - T_____, Franklin, 1993 (Box 18, Folder 197)
  - Tamagno, Caroline, 1997-2001 (Box 18, Folder 198)
  - Tanning, Dorothea, 1973 October 27 (Box 18, Folder 199)
  - Theodorakis, Mikis, 1966 August 16 (Box 18, Folder 200)
  - Thomas Gibson Fine Art Gallery, 1992-1999 (Box 18, Folder 201)
  - [Tigretti-Berthoud], Therese, 1990-1998 (Box 18, Folder 202)
  - Toklas, Alice B., 1946-1962 (Box 18, Folder 203)
  - "U" General, 1993-1996 (Box 19, Folder 204)
  - "V" General, 1993-2000, undated (Box 19, Folder 205)
  - Vail, Karole, 1993, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 206-207)
    See also: Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum
  - Valentin, Curt, 1945, undated (Box 19, Folder 208)
  - Villas, James, 1994-1998 (Box 19, Folder 209)
  - Villon, Jacques, 1958 December 2 (Box 19, Folder 210)
  - Vinaver, Michel, 1947-1958 (Box 19, Folder 211)
  - "W" General, 1953-1998 (Box 19, Folder 212-213)
  - Waldner, Lulu de, 1992-1997 (Box 19, Folder 214)
  - Watson, Peter, 1949-1951 (Box 19, Folder 215)
  - Welch, Jack, 1990-1996 (Box 19, Folder 216-217)
  - Wescott, Glenway, 1952-1963 (Box 20, Folder 218)
  - Wheeler, Monroe, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 219)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1954 December (Box 20, Folder 220)
  - Willenbecher, John, 1993-1999 (Box 20, Folder 221)
  - Wilson, Angus, 1950-1951 (Box 20, Folder 222)
  - Windham, Donald, 1949 November 17 (Box 20, Folder 223)
  - Woodhead, Robin, 1994 (Box 20, Folder 224)
  - Yakovleff, M., 1943 December 21 (Box 20, Folder 225)
  - The Yale Review, 1992, 1996 (Box 20, Folder 226)
  - Yale University Press, 2000 (Box 20, Folder 227)
  - "Z" General, 1995-1997 (Box 20, Folder 228)
  - _____, Carmen, outgoing, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 229)
  - Unidentified, 1940s-1950s (Box 20, Folder 230)
  - Unidentified, 1990s (Box 20, Folder 231-233)
  - Unidentified, 1990s (Box 21, Folder 234-236)
  - Unidentified "excerpt of a letter to a friend", 2002 May 28 (Box 21, Folder 237)
  - Other papers found with correspondence (Box 21, Folder 238)
- Writings, 1917-2003; Series II; 18.76 linear feet (48 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Writings of James Lord, and Writings of Others.
  Series II contains research material, drafts, proofs, and correspondence related to the writings of James Lord from the 1960s to 2003. Much of the material relates to Lord's many writings on Alberto Giacometti, including notes taken during interviews and source documents relating to Giacometti's life. Other files relate to Lord's memoirs, including letters from his mother that he used as source material for Six Exceptional Women.
  - Writings of James Lord
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - "Absolute Balthus," "for Venice catalogue," draft, autograph manuscript (copies), undated (Box 22, Folder 239-240)
    - "Alberto Giacometti at Home," draft, autograph manuscript (copy), circa 1997 (Box 22, Folder 241)
    - Alberto Giacometti: Myth, Magic, and the Man, review, draft, autograph manuscript, 2003 (Box 22, Folder 242)
    - "Alberto's Tantrum," printed version, corrected (copy), 1995 (Box 22, Folder 243)
    - "Beyond Horizon: Sonia Orwell and Peter Watson," draft, autograph manuscript (copy), circa 1997 (Box 22, Folder 244)
    - "Blame it on the afterbirth," printed version, 2003 (Box 22, Folder 245)
    - "The boy who wrote 'NO'," French translation, printed version, 1964 (Box 22, Folder 246)
    - "Diego," Cultura, draft, autograph manuscript, 2002 August 1 (Box 22, Folder 247)
    - "An Elder Statesman of the Art World," draft, autograph manuscript, 2003 (Box 22, Folder 248)
    - "Ethel de Croisset, Civilization's Friend," draft, autograph manuscript (copy), circa 2001 (Box 22, Folder 249)
    - A Farewell to Genius
      - Draft, autograph manuscript, 1995 (Box 22, Folder 250-252)
      - Fragment of draft, autograph manuscript (copy), undated (Box 22, Folder 253)
    - Giacometti: A Biography
      - Notebooks 1-11, 1970 (Box 23, Folder 254-265)
      - Notebooks 12-22, 1970 (Box 24, Folder 266-277)
      - Notebooks 23-35, 1970 (Box 25, Folder 278-289)
      - Notebooks 36-47, 1970 (Box 26, Folder 290-301)
      - Notebooks 48-57, 1970-1971 (Box 27, Folder 302-311)
      - Notebooks 58-68, 1971-1972 (Box 28, Folder 312-322)
      - Notebooks 69-80, 1972-1973 (Box 29, Folder 323-333)
      - Notebooks 81-91, 1973-1981 (Box 30, Folder 334-344)
      - Notebooks 92-93, 1981-1986 (Box 31, Folder 345-346)
      - Notebook: List of Conversations, undated (Box 31, Folder 347)
      - Notebook: Acknowledgments, undated (Box 31, Folder 348)
      - Notebook: Documents, undated (Box 31, Folder 349)
      - "Giacometti notebooks", undated; 3 notebooks (Box 31, Folder 350)
      - "Notes and sketches", undated (Box 31, Folder 351)
      - "Catalog and photographs", undated (Box 31, Folder 352)
      - "Research material", 1982-1983 (Box 31, Folder 353)
      - "Worksheets and notes: Revisions and end", undated (Box 31, Folder 354)
      - "Last days: Notes", undated (Box 31, Folder 355)
      - Photographs of busts by Jacop Epstein, undated (Box 31, Folder 356)
      - Research files, undated (Box 32, Folder 357-367)
      - Research files (continued), undated (Box 33, Folder 368-373)
      - Research files (continued), undated (Box 34, Folder 374-380)
      - Research files (continued), undated (Box 35, Folder 381-386)
      - Research files (continued), undated (Box 36, Folder 387-392)
      - Research files (continued), undated (Box 37, Folder 393-397)
      - Research files (continued), undated (Box 38, Folder 398-401)
      - Research files (continued), undated (Box 39, Folder 402-408)
      - "Identification of documents referred to by number in Notes & Sources section", undated (Box 40, Folder 409)
      - Documents numbered 1-426, 1917-1964 (Box 40, Folder 410-435)
      - Documents numbered 427-590, 1964-1983 (Box 41, Folder 436-459)
      - "Original manuscript" (pages 1-645), undated (Box 42, Folder 460-463)
      - Draft, autograph manuscript (pages 1-359), undated (Box 42, Folder 464-465)
      - Draft, autograph manuscript (continued) (pages 360-1200), undated (Box 43, Folder 466-470)
      - Draft, autograph manuscript (continued) (pages 1201-2089), undated (Box 44, Folder 471-475)
      - Draft, autograph manuscript (continued) (pages 2090-2879), undated (Box 45, Folder 476-480)
      - Draft, autograph manuscript (continued) (pages 2880-3199), 1982, undated (Box 46, Folder 481-482)
      - Typescript (original and electrostat copy) with author's corrections (Chapters 1-13), circa 1985 (Box 47, Folder 483-492)
      - Typescript (original and electrostat copy) with author's corrections (Chapters 1-13), circa 1985 (Box 48, Folder 493-495)
      - Typescript (original and photocopy) (Chapters 1-13), circa 1985 (Box 49, Folder 496-501)
      - Typescript (photocopy) (pages 1085-1155), circa 1985 (Box 49, Folder 502)
      - Typescript (photocopy) (pages 1-212), circa 1985 (Box 50, Folder 503-504)
      - Typescript, duplicate pages (pages 798-1369), circa 1986 (Box 50, Folder 505-524)
      - Setting typescript, undated (Box 51, Folder 525-529)
      - Setting typescript: Bibliography, undated (Box 52, Folder 530)
      - Setting typescript: Acknowledgments, undated (Box 52, Folder 531)
      - Galley proofs, circa 1986 (Box 53, Folder 532)
      - Galley proofs (continued), circa 1986 (Box 54, Folder 533)
      - Printed version, corrected by the author and bound with related manuscripts, circa 1987 (Box 55, Folder 534)
      - Preface to a French edition, typescript (photocopy), 1995 (Box 55, Folder 535)
      - Printed version, corrected by James Lord, 2002 (Box 55, Folder 536)
    - A Giacometti Portrait
      - Notes, undated (Box 56, Folder 537)
        "Manuscript notes used for Chapters on 17th and 18th sittings -- all rest destroyed."
      - Setting copy, undated (Box 56, Folder 538)
      - Galley proofs, undated (Box 56, Folder 539-540)
      - Preface to the French edition by Diego Giacometti, manuscript, undated (Box 56, Folder 541)
    - A Gift for Admiration, proofs, 1997-1998 (Box 57, Folder 542-550)
    - "A Gift of Death," autograph manuscript, 1954 (Box 57, Folder 551)
    - "Making Memoirs," draft, autograph manuscript (fragment), 1997, undated (Box 57, Folder 552)
    - "A Matter of Life or Death" (short story)
      - Draft, autograph manuscript, 1954 (Box 58, Folder 553)
      - Draft, typescript, circa 1954 (Box 58, Folder 554)
    - Mythic Giacometti
      - Draft, autograph manuscript, and notes, undated (Box 58, Folder 555-558)
      - Draft, typescript, undated (Box 58, Folder 559)
      - Draft, "revised typescript", 2002 July 24 (Box 58, Folder 560)
      - Proof, 2002 October 11 (Box 58, Folder 561-562)
      - Proofs, 2003-2004 (Box 59, Folder 563-566)
      - "Revised version," printout, undated (Box 59, Folder 567)
      - Review, printed version, 2005 (Box 59, Folder 568)
    - "Peggy's palazzo," printout, 1995 (Box 59, Folder 569)
    - Picasso and Dora: A Personal Memoir
      - French translation, draft, computer printout, 1998 (Box 59, Folder 570)
      - Reviews, printed versions, 1993-1994 (Box 59, Folder 571)
    - Picasso: The Communist Years, by Gertje R. Utley, Review by James Lord
      - Draft, autograph manuscript, circa 2001 (Box 60, Folder 572)
      - Draft, autograph manuscript (copy), circa 2001 (Box 60, Folder 573)
      - Printed version, 2001 March 30 (Box 60, Folder 574)